<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>heisenberg</title>
    <description>Chemistry, Music, Life</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2023 23:19:53 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Dec 2023 23:19:53 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.3.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>US National Chemistry Olympiad</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Passionate about chemistry, I have participated in a prestigious science competition known as the USNCO. In this post, I will provide key information on how to crack the USNCO. Hope this benefits you and Merry Christmas!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-usnco&quot;&gt;About USNCO&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;USNCO or United States National Chemistry Olympiad is a chemistry competition for high school students that starts of at the local levels, then the national level, and finally the international level. Moving up levels requires an excellent performance at the previous levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;local-level&quot;&gt;Local Level&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the local level, there is only one exam - the aptly named &lt;strong&gt;local exam&lt;/strong&gt;. A multiple-choice exam with 60 questions and a time limit of 110 minutes, the local exam covers a wide variety of topics, most of which are AP Chemistry exam topics. However, the difficulty in this exam comes from the questions that cover topics not on the AP Chemistry exam and the questions that involve clever applications of AP Chemistry exam concepts. If you do well, you will proceed to the national level. However, if more than two students from your school qualify to proceed to the national level, then only the two highest scoring students will proceed to the national level. When I attempted USNCO last year, 3 students from my school qualified that included me, but unfortunately I could not make it to the national level because of this rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;national-level&quot;&gt;National Level&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the national level, there are three national exams that must be taken (it’s one national exam with three parts, but it truly feels like three exams).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part/exam is another multiple-choice exam. The topics are not that much different than those at the local level, but the questions get significantly more difficult and sometimes require some insane ways of applying concepts. Even more challenging is the time constraint, 60 questions again, but now you only have 90 minutes to complete them. At the end of the exam there is a quick survey that you can complete, and it does not affect your score on the exam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second part/exam is composed of eight free-response questions (eight questions with MANY parts, that is) and has a time limit of 105 minutes. The difficulty is on par with the first part/exam, but now you cannot rely on lucky guesses to score you a few extra points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final part/exam is a lab practical. A lab practical is where you will perform an actual lab procedure or experiment to collect data to answer some lab questions given to you. In this lab practical you are given two questions (again, with many parts to each question) to complete within 90 minutes.
If you really hit it out of the park, if you are in the top 20 at the national level, welcome to study camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;study-camp&quot;&gt;Study Camp&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the final level before the famous &lt;strong&gt;International Chemistry Olympiad (IChO)&lt;/strong&gt;. This study camp is full of intense studying and practice. The top four students in study camp will represent the United States team in IChO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;icho&quot;&gt;IChO&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AP Chemistry topics will not cut it anymore. There is not much information about IChO, but the few recent IChO exams that I have reviewed are beyond anything I have ever seen. Physical chemistry, biochemistry, materials chemistry, no field of chemistry is left out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-prepare&quot;&gt;How to prepare&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you aspire to make it to the national and international levels of the Chemistry Olympiad, keep reading. Preparing for USNCO requires knowledge of many topics. Practice the topics listed below to ensure that you can complete USNCO exams within their time limits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;stoichiometry--solutions&quot;&gt;Stoichiometry &amp;amp; Solutions&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stoichiometry is often tested in questions 1-6 of USNCO multiple-choice exams. Stoichiometry is not difficult to learn, as it is applying basic arithmetic and algebra to quantify various amounts in chemistry. The difficulties that come with stoichiometry problems in USNCO exams include whether you can find the shortcut to solve the question quickly and the presence of other topics that are mixed with stoichiometric problems. A strong knowledge of solutions is also required. Knowledge of solutions includes solubilities of salts and the dissolution of salts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;descriptivelaboratory&quot;&gt;Descriptive/Laboratory&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Descriptive/Laboratory chemistry is often tested in questions 7-12 of USNCO multiple-choice exams. Knowledge of descriptive/laboratory chemistry includes the uses of various laboratory glassware, the color of ions in solution, the flame test, reactions of different elements and compounds in liquids, error analysis, iodometry, and many other analytical techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;states-of-matter&quot;&gt;States of Matter&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;States of matter are often tested in questions 13-18 of USNCO multiple-choice exams. Knowledge of states of matter is very broad, including ideal and non-ideal gas laws, intermolecular forces, boiling points, crystal structures, phase changes, and phase diagrams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;thermodynamics&quot;&gt;Thermodynamics&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thermodynamics is often tested in questions 19-24 of USNCO multiple-choice exams. Knowledge of thermodynamics includes comparison of thermodynamic properties for various substances at various phases of matter and equations for heat/enthalpy, entropy, and Gibbs free energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;kinetics&quot;&gt;Kinetics&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kinetics is often tested in questions 25-30 of USNCO multiple-choice exams. Knowledge of kinetics includes the equation for the rate of a reaction, determining the change in concentrations of an occurring reaction, determining what the rate of a reaction is dependent upon, and the various properties of kinetically different reactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;equilibria&quot;&gt;Equilibria&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Equilibria are often tested in questions 31-36 of USNCO multiple-choice exams. Knowledge of equilibria include Le Chatelier’s principle, determining whether a reaction is at equilibrium or not, equations involving the equilibrium constant, and determining the concentrations and pressures of both reactants and products at equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;redox&quot;&gt;Redox&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Redox is often tested in questions 37-42 of USNCO multiple-choice exams. Knowledge of redox includes oxidation states, determining oxidants and reductants, balancing redox reactions, electrochemistry, and any equations related to cell potentials in electrochemistry. This section tends to be difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;atomic-structureperiodicity&quot;&gt;Atomic Structure/Periodicity&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Atomic structure/periodicity is often tested in questions 43-48 of USNCO multiple-choice exams. Knowledge of atomic structure/periodicity includes electron configurations, quantum numbers, periodic trends, fundamental principles about electrons, various atomic models and their equations, and radioactive decay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;bondingmolecular-structure&quot;&gt;Bonding/Molecular Structure&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonding/molecular structure is often tested in questions 49-54 of USNCO multiple-choice exams. Knowledge of bonding/molecular structure includes VSEPR theory, MO theory, valence bond theory, hybridization, dipoles, crystal field theory, and isomers in coordination compounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;organicbiochemistry&quot;&gt;Organic/Biochemistry&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organic/biochemistry is often tested in questions 55-60 of USNCO multiple-choice exams. Knowledge of organic/biochemistry includes organic chemistry I, II, and III.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Knowledge of all these topics will also help you answer the free-response exam at the national level. Lab experience prior to the lab practical exam at the national level is highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tips-and-tricks&quot;&gt;Tips and Tricks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only tips and tricks for this competition are the tried-and-true ones that I am listing below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do the easy questions first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guess if you do not know the answer to the question.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you can, avoid using intuition. Many of the questions can be misleading if math is involved.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is a time constraint, dwelling is a surefire way to failure. Be mindful of time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lot to know to compete in USNCO. I found the below resources helpful in the preparation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;general-chemistry&quot;&gt;General Chemistry&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A good starting point is the book &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Chemistry-Steven-S-Zumdahl/dp/1133611095&quot;&gt;Chemistry by Zumdahl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Chemical-Principles-Insight-Peter-Atkins/dp/1464183953&quot;&gt;Chemical Principles: The Quest for Insight by Atkins&lt;/a&gt; is challenging, but definitely worth studying.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;organic-chemistry&quot;&gt;Organic Chemistry&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start here on the &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.masterorganicchemistry.com/&quot;&gt;Master Organic Chemistry&lt;/a&gt; website&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Organic-Chemistry-David-R-Klein/dp/1119659590&quot;&gt;Organic Chemistry by Klein&lt;/a&gt; is a good read&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Aspiring for IChO? Read &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Organic-Chemistry-Jonathan-Clayden/dp/0199270295&quot;&gt;Organic Chemistry by Clayden&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;other-resources&quot;&gt;Other Resources&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://chem.isodn.org/resources&quot;&gt;CODSite&lt;/a&gt; for all other competitive chemistry needs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@CODSYoutube/videos&quot;&gt;Insightful videos&lt;/a&gt; from CODSite&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.acs.org/education/students/highschool/olympiad/prepare-for-exams.html&quot;&gt;Past USNCO exams&lt;/a&gt; that can be done for practice and prep&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck, and may the best chemists win.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Dec 2023 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>/us-national-chemistry-olympiad/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/us-national-chemistry-olympiad/</guid>
        
        
        <category>chemistry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chess Champions</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;So, my school team competed in the 2023 Washington Mini-Teams chess tournament, and we won! The path to victory was a precarious five-match battle, and I am here to tell you all about it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-hectic-morning&quot;&gt;A Hectic Morning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set an alarm to wake up for the tournament, but my excitedness woke me up at six in the morning. I quickly grabbed my tournament fee money, some snacks, and planned to drive to the chess tournament. However, my parents were not comfortable with me driving so much on the highway, so Pranav managed to pick me up from my house at the last minute. My inactivity in chess tournaments had made my chess skills a bit dull, so I was hoping to use this tournament to determine where I stood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;game-round-1&quot;&gt;Game Round 1&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;iframe id=&quot;11306337&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;border:none;&quot; src=&quot;//www.chess.com/emboard?id=11306337&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script&gt;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,e=&gt;{e[&apos;data&apos;]&amp;&amp;&quot;11306337&quot;===e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;id&apos;]&amp;&amp;document.getElementById(`${e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;id&apos;]}`)&amp;&amp;(document.getElementById(`${e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;id&apos;]}`).style.height=`${e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;frameHeight&apos;]+30}px`)});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the random pairings for the first round, the school team that played my school team comprised of beginner chess players. I won my game quickly as white, giving me time to eat some snacks before the next game started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;game-round-2&quot;&gt;Game Round 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;iframe id=&quot;11306355&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;border:none;&quot; src=&quot;//www.chess.com/emboard?id=11306355&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script&gt;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,e=&gt;{e[&apos;data&apos;]&amp;&amp;&quot;11306355&quot;===e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;id&apos;]&amp;&amp;document.getElementById(`${e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;id&apos;]}`)&amp;&amp;(document.getElementById(`${e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;id&apos;]}`).style.height=`${e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;frameHeight&apos;]+30}px`)});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played black, and this game was stressful. The person I played was unrated, meaning he did not have an official chess rating. With my experience of unrated players being that the unrated players were hidden masters of the game, I was quite nervous during the game. I stopped notating due to time trouble, but I still remember the game to be intense. The game was full of personal mistakes that made me feel as if I were going to be quitely suffocated in a cramped position. However, I managed to gain some activty of the queenside, but my opponent&apos;s 22. Nd2 made me wish I had moved my rook off of a8. Low on time, I gave up my advanced knight, losing most of my advantage. The game went on with me almost causing a three-fold repetition, creating a passed pawn, and overpowering my opponent&apos;s major pieces. Finally, my opponent resigned before my passed pawn became a queen. There was a lunch break after this game, giving me time to relax before my third game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;game-round-3&quot;&gt;Game Round 3&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;iframe id=&quot;11306359&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;border:none;&quot; src=&quot;//www.chess.com/emboard?id=11306359&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script&gt;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,e=&gt;{e[&apos;data&apos;]&amp;&amp;&quot;11306359&quot;===e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;id&apos;]&amp;&amp;document.getElementById(`${e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;id&apos;]}`)&amp;&amp;(document.getElementById(`${e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;id&apos;]}`).style.height=`${e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;frameHeight&apos;]+30}px`)});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My third game was an awkward one. I played white, and the game went okay until my opponent blundered a pawn with 15. Re8, and I left to go to the bathroom after I played my 17th move. I came back to the board only to see that I only had five minutes on my clock. Thanfully, the time control included a time delay; I had five seconds for each move before the time on my clock would begin counting down. I played quickly from then on, and my opponent, for some strange reason, helped me by trading all of his pieces. The resulting game was a king and pawn endgame where I was a pawn up. Such a winning endgame is often taught early on in the life of a chess player, so my opponent resigned soon after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;game-round-4&quot;&gt;Game Round 4&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;iframe id=&quot;11306361&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;border:none;&quot; src=&quot;//www.chess.com/emboard?id=11306361&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script&gt;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,e=&gt;{e[&apos;data&apos;]&amp;&amp;&quot;11306361&quot;===e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;id&apos;]&amp;&amp;document.getElementById(`${e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;id&apos;]}`)&amp;&amp;(document.getElementById(`${e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;id&apos;]}`).style.height=`${e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;frameHeight&apos;]+30}px`)});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth game was wild and lousily played by me. I played black against an opponent who had a rating of about 1200. However, opponent had been practicing for a few years, so my opponent definetly did not play like a 1200. The opening led to a Breyer defense in the Ruy Lopez, and I had unfortunately forgotten how to play the Breyer defense. After many threats by my opponent and a blunder by me that my opponent luckily did not see, I opened up the position and won some material. We went into time trouble, and I won more material from then on while avoiding some very scary mating threats by my opponent&apos;s aggressive knight and queen. After a few trades, I emerged a rook up in an easy-to-win endgame. My opponent resigned immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;game-round-5&quot;&gt;Game Round 5&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;iframe id=&quot;11306363&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width:100%;border:none;&quot; src=&quot;//www.chess.com/emboard?id=11306363&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script&gt;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,e=&gt;{e[&apos;data&apos;]&amp;&amp;&quot;11306363&quot;===e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;id&apos;]&amp;&amp;document.getElementById(`${e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;id&apos;]}`)&amp;&amp;(document.getElementById(`${e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;id&apos;]}`).style.height=`${e[&apos;data&apos;][&apos;frameHeight&apos;]+30}px`)});&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the toughest game for me. I was quite tired by this point, and I had run out of snacks. Dehydrated due to the fact that I had lost my water bottle (I later found it in the lost and found), I wasted away up-the-exchange advantage, eventually giving up the material advantage out of fear from the wrath my opponents&apos; knights would impose upon my king. Both of us got into severe time trouble. I created a very advanced passed pawn, and my opponent found a tactic that made him win a pawn (if I took the pawn, I would be checkmated). I had three seconds left on my clock, and I was dodging very sneaky checkmate threats by overworking my pieces. Thankfully, while I had to give up some of my minor pieces and was down in material, I gained enough passed pawns to overpower his pieces with some very neat sacrifices. With my opponent having no way to stop the promotion of my passed pawn nor a way to utilize his passed pawns from my material sacrifices, he resigned. This was one of the only tournaments that I got a perfect score. Pranav also won all his games, but Blessington lost his Round 5 game. Blessington was up a full queen, but a last-ditch, easy-to-defuse checkmate trap by his opponent, combined with Blessington&apos;s half-closed eyes, led to a tragic loss for our team. Such tragic games have happened to me as well. It also explains why Blessington did not smile in the photo where our school team held the first place trophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-standings&quot;&gt;Final Standings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;shadow-lg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/mini-teams-final-standing-2023.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tournament final standings&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;The final standings of the chess tournament.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My school team won first place in the tournament with a score of 14/15. The school team in second place was so far behind us that if there was another round in the tournament, my school team would win no matter the outcome of the final round! Pranav and I were the only ones who scored a perfect 5/5 in the tournament, and we were awarded for our excellent performance with a nice medal. While Blessington unfortunately did not get the medal he deserved, his chess rating saw a healthy increase from his still successful score of 4/5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I know my chess skills are not rusty, I will seek to play in more chess tournaments and improve my chess ranking. May the best player win!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2023 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>/chess-champions/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/chess-champions/</guid>
        
        
        <category>chess</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>From Alchemy to Chemistry</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Alchemy was chemistry in its infancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everybody knows what fire is, it’s what happens when you burn something. Often used for cooking and warmth, fire comes from a chemical reaction called combustion. The combustion reaction is one of the first known chemical reactions that was controlled and utilized by humans. A combustion reaction is simple: you burn something with carbon and hydrogen (and maybe oxygen), and an immense amount of heat is released as the burning compound reacts with oxygen in the air to create carbon dioxide and water vapor (yes, fire makes water).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the first metals humans obtained in their pure form were copper, silver, and gold. Early on, humans learned that metals could be isolated and useful compounds could be created by heating metal ores and mixtures of compounds, respectively. This process gave rise to an early form of chemistry and metallurgy. As humans became acquainted with primitive chemical processes, a new field, often now called an early form of chemistry, was born: alchemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;shadow-lg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/alchemy-types.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Two types of alchemy (joke)&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;The birth of organic and inorganic chemistry.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alchemy was a field devoted to determining a way to make ordinary materials into gold, a highly valuable commodity. Nowadays, we know that this is not possible through chemical processes. Elements are substances that cannot be changed through chemical processes, and alchemists DEFINITELY did not know about nuclear processes that could make gold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As alchemists tried and tried and tried to create some magical substance that could turn everything into gold, alchemists accidentally discovered early chemical concepts, analytical techniques, and even new elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alchemist Jãbir ibn Hayyãn discovered that some substances could be broken down, while others could not. Other Arab alchemists discovered that each substance gave a colored flame when burned, what we now call the &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flame_test&quot;&gt;flame test&lt;/a&gt;. Alchemist Hennig Brand discovered the element phosphorus by boiling down his urine; he thought the golden color of urine held the secret to the magical substance that could turn anything into gold. Alchemists provided the necessary foundations for alchemy to transcend into chemistry. All they needed was some fresh air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;shadow-lg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/alchemy-explicit.png&quot; alt=&quot;The magic of Alchemy&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Alchemy had its flaws.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important theory in alchemy called the &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phlogiston_theory&quot;&gt;Phlogiston theory&lt;/a&gt; claimed the existence of a substance called phlogiston. Burning metal ores with a phlogiston-rich substance such as coal produced a metal that was infused with phlogiston from the coal. As metals rust, they lose their infused phlogiston, causing the metal to weaken and fall apart. The problem with this theory was that when metals rusted and LOST their infused phlogiston, the metals GAINED mass. The discovery of numerous gasses during the late 18th century would not only disprove the phlogiston theory, but it would also disprove the fundamentality of a common substance: air. In 1766, chemist Henry Cavendish reacted metal zinc and iron with strong acids and created what he called “inflammable gas” (hydrogen gas). Soon after, chemists Joseph Black and Joseph Priestley discovered phlogisticated air (carbon dioxide) and dephlogisticated air (oxygen gas), respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What made these discoveries so important was that a chemist named &lt;strong&gt;Antoine Lavoisier&lt;/strong&gt; discovered that air was absorbed by metals to create rust, refuting the phlogiston theory. The discovery of oxygen gas made Antoine Lavoisier discover that air was not a fundamental substance, and a part of the air – oxygen gas – was the gas responsible for rusting metals. The discovery of oxygen gas also helped Antoine Lavoisier establish the law of conservation of mass. The law of conservation of mass states that mass is neither created nor lost in any process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If everything in chemistry is explained in a satisfactory manner without the help of phlogiston, it is by that reason alone infinitely probable that the principle does not exist; that it is a hypothetical body, a gratuitous supposition; indeed, it is in the principles of good logic, not to multiply bodies without necessity.” - &lt;strong&gt;Antoine Lavoisier&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the theory of phlogiston gone, chemistry was born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the work of Antoine Lavoisier, chemistry has grown remarkably. Batteries have been created, electricity has been used to isolate reactive elements, the theory of atoms has been established, subatomic particles have been discovered, even Albert Einstein contributed to chemistry by showing how the movement of atoms cause very light particles to move seemingly randomly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a series I LOVE on the history of chemistry, you can watch the series &lt;strong&gt;The Mystery of Matter: Search for the Elements&lt;/strong&gt;, links below&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z3Gt5IOjAuc&quot;&gt;The Mystery of Matter: “OUT OF THIN AIR”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wbuDmY5gpXQ&quot;&gt;The Mystery of Matter: “UNRULY ELEMENTS”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GWQZE0HPoAY&quot;&gt;The Mystery of Matter: “INTO THE ATOM”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2023 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>/alchemy-to-chemistry/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/alchemy-to-chemistry/</guid>
        
        
        <category>chemistry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What was that K-6 pin Oppenheimer wore?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;That is me, next to my organic chemistry professor &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.bellevuecollege.edu/ids/staff/jennie-mayer/&quot;&gt;Jennie Mayer&lt;/a&gt; on Halloween.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I dressed up as Oppenheimer, while professor Mayer dressed up as Mary Poppins. I had my tweed suit, brown tie, and the K-6 pin from the movie &lt;i&gt;Oppenheimer&lt;/i&gt;. To top it off, I wore a brown pork pie hat, just like the real Oppenheimer did. Many loved my costume, but I stumbled across a common question all the time: what does the K-6 on my pin mean?

&lt;p&gt;I had not actually thought about it: what DOES the K-6 on my pin mean? Some joked around and said it meant kindergarten to sixth grade, and that my costume was just a fancily dressed elementary school teacher. However, with the question stuck in my mind, I got to researching the K-6 pin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through my research, I have found that the K-6 pin was the identification number given to the real Oppenheimer when he worked at the secret Los Alamos Laboratory. Below is an actual image of Oppenheimer with this identification.

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;center&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/oppenheimer-k-6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;K-6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that the movie &lt;i&gt; &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.oppenheimermovie.com/&quot;&gt;Oppenheimer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; included the K-6 pin has grown my appreciation for the movie. To the custom-made silver New Mexico belt buckle, wide brown tie, and light brown pork pie hat, &lt;i&gt;Oppenheimer&lt;/i&gt; has definetly done its research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;center&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/cillian-murphy-k-6.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;K-6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a perfect main character, a perfect movie naturally follows ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... and inspires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Halloween!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/oppenheimer-k6/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/oppenheimer-k6/</guid>
        
        
        <category>life</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My musical journey</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;elementary-school&quot;&gt;Elementary School&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began my music journey in fourth grade. My school music teacher made the whole class learn the recorder to prepare for fifth grade, where we would be allowed to choose from many instruments. To make learning music more fun, I remember my school music teacher gave everyone a “Recorder Karate” book. Each page contained a song and a few fingerings for the recorder. Just like karate, there were white, yellow, orange, green, purple, blue, red, brown, and black belts that could be earned. The first song was a “White Belt” song, so playing the song well would earn you a white belt. Each “belt” was a rubber band of whatever color of belt you earned wrapped around the end of the recorder. As you progress through the &lt;em&gt;Recorder Karate&lt;/em&gt; book, the songs get more challenging, but the fact that you earned a colored “belt” was enough to get me to practice my recorder every day. Eventually, I got every “belt”, with my black belt being my greatest achievement at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;shadow-lg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/recorder-belts.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Shiv&apos;s recorder from 4th grade&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;My recorder from 4th grade, honored with the 9 belts of progression.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fifth grade, students had a choice between joining band or orchestra. My perception of bands at that time came from marching bands, and I definetly did not want to march and move awkwardly as I played my instrument, so I joined orchesta. I took the violin because it was the least hassle to carry. I felt bad for the cello and double bass players as they lugged their large instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The violin was fun as I learned the fingerings on each string. It was when I got into middle school when I decided that I wanted more diversity in my music experience, so I switched to band. Amongst all the wind instruments, I spent hours trying to determine which instrument I would play. I landed on the flute since it was small and did not require delicate reeds that always need moistening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;middle-school&quot;&gt;Middle School&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I quickly learned that playing wind instruments is different than playing string instruments. There was no bow to play the sound for me, I had to shape my mouth correctly and blow into the flute. For the first month I was met with failure as I tried to muster one note. I began greatly disliking band, wanting to return to orchestra and continue playing my violin. Unfortunately, I could not change my class from band to orchestra, meaning I would have to continue playing the flute until the end of the school year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, I did eventually get the hang of the flute. I had even grown to become passionate for playing the flute, so I continued band into seventh grade. By this time, I thought I played very well. My father also taught me some Hindi film tunes to play on the flute. Seventh grade saw me audition for entrance into the Bellevue Youth Symphony Orchestra, but I did not get accepted. I talked to my father about getting me flute lessons to improve my flute skills. That is how I met Mrs. Rose, my flute teacher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Under Mrs. Rose&apos;s training, my flute skills improved immediately. There were numerous things that I was previously doing incorrectly on the flute that Mrs. Rose had me correct. There is no substitute for a good teacher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;shadow-lg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/wmea-shiv-2020.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;WMEA Junior 2020 - Baker Band&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By eighth grade, I had become confident in my flute skills, and I was accepted into the Bellevue Youth Symphony Orchestra. I also competed in some music competitions in my school. My highest point in Middle school music was when I got to play at the state level in WMEA All-State Junior in February 2020, which was right before COVID shut everything down. My school closed down for the rest of the year, and all of the music events I was involved in were cancelled. By the end of the school year, I quit Bellevue Youth Symphony Orchestra to focus on my new chapter of life: high school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;high-school&quot;&gt;High School&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;shadow-lg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/shiv-bansuri.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Shiv playing bansuri&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Picture of me playing the bansuri on a stage recital arranged by my Indian classical music teacher Satyajit ji (&apos;ji&apos; as a suffix to the name is used to convey respect to a person in Hindi).&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In high school, I continued to play the flute and have lessons on it, but since I quit playing for the high school band in 9th grade, playing the flute took a backseat as I was introduced to a new instrument: the Indian flute (bansuri).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My father introduced me to the bansuri since he wanted me to play Hindi film songs, and I took a liking to the bansuri because it felt and was played similar to the flute. I was fortunate to have Satyajit Limaye, an Indian classical music teacher close to where I lived. I started lessons with him. On my first class, he asked me to play what I knew on the western flute. After hearing me play, he told my father that I would quickly pick up the bansuri.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I started playing the bansuri, I found one critical difference: holes in the flute were either fully open or fully closed, while holes in the bansuri were either fully open, fully closed, or half-open (or half-closed, which one is it?). Looking at how far my fingers could stretch, Satyajit ji got me started on a ‘G’ flute. Over a period of time, my fingers got used to the stretching. With practice, playing bansuri became second nature to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;-and-beyond&quot;&gt;… and beyond&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I look back over these years, learning to play 4 musical instruments was quite a journey, but this journey is not over. I want to take my musical skills, engagement, and appreciation to the next level. Thus, I plan to do a minor in music in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see what is in store for me next.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Aug 2023 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/my-musical-journey/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/my-musical-journey/</guid>
        
        
        <category>music</category>
        
        <category>life</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chemistry of Colors</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“Colors are the smiles of Nature.” - &lt;i&gt;Leigh Hunt&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…and true colors are the smiles of chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-brief-history-of-colors&quot;&gt;A Brief History of Colors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colors have been used before writing was invented. Over 200 thousand years ago, early humans ground up rocks and minerals like hematite, also known as iron (iii) oxide for cave paintings and object decoreation. Hematite contains Fe&lt;sup&gt;3+&lt;/sup&gt; ions, which have a reddish-brown color. Early humans began doing primitive chemistry to create other colors. Adding water to hematite created limonite, a mixture of multiple minerals that has a yellow color.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;shadow-lg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/limonite.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Limonite rock&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first synthetic pigments humans made was Egyptian Blue. As the name suggests, it was made by early Egyptians around 5000 years ago. Blue-colored substances are rare in nature, so Egyptian blue allowed for a synthetic substitute for obtaining a blue color. Egyptian blue is made by heating a ground-up mixture of sand, chalk, a source of copper, and embalming salts to about 900&lt;sup&gt;o&lt;/sup&gt;C for 10 to 100 hours!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;shadow-lg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/egyptian-blue.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Egyptian Blue Color&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jumping ahead to the 19th century, many famous artists like Vincent van Gogh came to prominence. To create paintings, artists used paints that were, and still are, created by mixing a dried and ground-up pigment, a solvent to make the paint liquid, and a binder that keeps the pigment and solvent from separating. Vincent van Gogh&apos;s famous painting at the beginning of this post uses a multitude of compounds to create color. Black was made from crushed sources of carbon such as charred bones, white was made from lead salts (which we now know are toxic), red was made from toxic mercury compounds, blue was made from iron compounds, yellow was made from a mixture of lead and chromium, and a deep green was made from a mixture of copper and arsenic (arsenic being toxic, many artists, &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.artpublikamag.com/post/when-color-kills-toxic-pigments-through-the-ages&quot;&gt;including Vincent van Gogh, grew insane from arsenic poisoning&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Further research: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CtiKkJrB-ag&quot;&gt;PBS Studios - The Chemistry of Color&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-basics-of-color&quot;&gt;The Basics of Color&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we can understand how chemistry plays a role in coloring compounds, we must learn why colors exist in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our eyes see a range of light called the visible spectrum; light outside of the visible spectrum range is invisible to our eyes. When an object has a color, it means that the object does not absorb, but reflect that color. For example, a red book does not absorb red light, so red light reflects off the book and reaches our eye, making the book look red.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, if an object absorbs a color, the object’s color will be the color opposite to the absorbed color on the color wheel (two colors that are opposite to each other on the color wheel are called complementary colors).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;shadow-lg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/color-wheel.png&quot; alt=&quot;Color wheel showing complementary colors&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the color wheel above, an object that absorbs orange light will look blue, and an object that absorbs blue-green light will have an orange-red look. Transparent objects do not reflect light, but instead let unabsorbed light pass through itself. Black objects absorb almost all visible light, and white objects reflect almost all visible light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-organic-side-of-colors&quot;&gt;The Organic Side of Colors&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what gives compounds their color?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lycopene (a red pigment found in tomatoes), zeaxanthin (an orange-red compound found in wolfberries), lutein (a yellow compound found in egg yolks), chlorophyll b (a green compound found in plants), indigotin (a blue compound in indigo dye), and petunidin (a purple compound found in some grapes) are organic compounds whose colors range throughout the visible spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cause for the variety of color? Conjugated pi bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pi bonds are in double and triple bonds in molecules. Conjugated pi bonds mean that there is an alternating pattern of double/triple bond, single bond, double/triple bond, single bond, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;shadow-lg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/carrots-c40h56.png&quot; alt=&quot;Molecule of Beta Carotene&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Molecule of Beta Carotene showing an alternating pattern of 11 double bonds (conjugated pi bonds). It is orange-red in color and found in carrots.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compounds with a large continuous conjugated pi bond system generally absorb light in the visible spectrum. The larger the conjugated pi bond system, the longer the wavelength of light that is absorbed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because each pi bond has two energy levels: one in a bonding orbital and the other in an antibonding orbital. Each orbital holds up to two electrons, with the lower energy levels getting filled up before the higher energy levels. The bonding orbitals are the lower energy levels, while the antibonding orbitals are the higher energy levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, when there are &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; conjugated pi bonds in a conjugated pi bond system, there exist &lt;strong&gt;2n&lt;/strong&gt; electrons in the conjugated pi bond system, &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; bonding orbitals in the conjugated pi bond system, and &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt; antibonding orbitals in the conjugated pi bond system. In the image below, antibonding orbitals are marked with a &lt;sup&gt;&lt;strong&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;shadow-lg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/homo-lumo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Molecular Orbitals&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;HOMO = Highest Occupied Molecular Orbital, LUMO = Lowest Unoccupied Molecular Orbital&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wavelength of light increases going from violet to red to light. As the wavelength of light increases, the energy of the light decreases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, the conjugated pi bond system must have more than eight continuously conjugated pi bonds to go from absorbing UV light to visible light, producing a visible color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How about some examples?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;isophorone-colorless&quot;&gt;Isophorone (Colorless)&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;shadow-lg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/isophorone.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chemical structure of isophorone&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Isophorone has a conjugated pi bond system of only two conjugated pi bonds. It is colorless.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;lycopene-red&quot;&gt;Lycopene (Red)&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;shadow-lg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/lycopene.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chemical structure of lycopene&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Lycopene has a conjugated pi bond system of &lt;b&gt;11&lt;/b&gt; conjugated pi bonds. It looks red because it absorbs green light; green and red are complimentary colors.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;chlorophyll-b-green&quot;&gt;Chlorophyll b (Green)&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;shadow-lg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/chlorophyll-b.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chemical structure of chlorophyll b&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Chlorophyll b has a conjugated pi bond system of &lt;b&gt;13&lt;/b&gt; conjugated pi bonds. It looks green because it absorbs red light.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;zeaxanthin-yellow-orange&quot;&gt;Zeaxanthin (Yellow-Orange)&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;shadow-lg&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/zeaxanthin.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chemical structure of zeaxanthin&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Zeaxanthin has a conjugated pi bond system of &lt;b&gt;11&lt;/b&gt; conjugated pi bonds. It looks yellow-orange because it absorbs blue-violet light.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hold on a second! Both lycopene and zeaxanthin have a conjugated pi bond system of 11 conjugated pi bonds, so why do they have different colors?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the number of conjugated pi bonds in a conjugated pi bond system is not the only factor that determines the color of organic compounds. Whether the conjugated pi bonds are attached to different substituents/functional groups and the location of the conjugated pi bonds also affects the wavelength absorbed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, determining the number of conjugated pi bonds in a conjugated pi bond system is the primary factor in determining the color of most organic compounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fun fact:&lt;/strong&gt; Bleach reacts with colored organic compounds and destroys double bonds, causing the color of the compound to disappear or lighten. This is the reason why bleach gets rid of color in clothes. Your clothes still stay stained, however the stain simply no longer shows up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jul 2023 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/chemistry-of-colors/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/chemistry-of-colors/</guid>
        
        
        <category>chemistry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Markup your text with Markdown</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Not all content needs bell and whistles. Notepad style text is boring as well. This is where a formatting standard called &lt;strong&gt;Markdown&lt;/strong&gt; comes to the rescue. Markdown is a simple text based formatting that anyone can do using a simple text editor and when it is processed by the right rendering engine, you get formatted text. It is much simpler than &lt;strong&gt;html&lt;/strong&gt; and can very conveniently be used to write web based documents. You can learn markdown 101 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.markdownguide.org/basic-syntax/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; has all the details you would be interested in knowing about markdown, including its history. In this article I am sharing some of the more advanced things that you can do using markdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;special-formatting&quot;&gt;Special formatting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as bold and italics, you can also use some other special formatting in Markdown when the need arises, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;strike through&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Large dashes using &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;---&lt;/code&gt; which render as  — inline&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adding color using html like &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;font color=&quot;LimeGreen&quot;&amp;gt;This text is lime green!&amp;lt;/font&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; renders as &lt;font color=&quot;LimeGreen&quot;&gt;This text is Lime Green in color!&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;writing-code-blocks&quot;&gt;Writing code blocks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two types of code elements which can be inserted in Markdown, the first is inline, and the other is block. Inline code is formatted by wrapping any word or words in back-ticks, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;like this could be some inline code&lt;/code&gt;. Larger snippets of code can be displayed across multiple lines using triple back ticks followed by a name of the code language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;no-language-hint&quot;&gt;No language hint&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;.my-link {
    text-decoration: underline;
}
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;html&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-html highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;li&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;ml-1 mr-1&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;target=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;_blank&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;href=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;#&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;i&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; Here I come &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;/li&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;css&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-css highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;.highlight&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;.c&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;#999988&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;font-style&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;italic&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;.highlight&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;.err&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;#a61717&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;background-color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;#e3d2d2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;js&quot;&gt;JS&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-js highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// alertbar later&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;scroll&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;function &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;var&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;scrollTop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;y&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;280&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;.alertbar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;fadeIn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;.alertbar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&apos;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;fadeOut&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;});&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;python&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-python highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sh&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;Hello World&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sh&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reference-lists&quot;&gt;Reference lists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than the standard &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;[Text](url)&lt;/code&gt; markdown format, another way to insert links in markdown is using reference lists. You might want to use this style of linking to cite reference material like in a publication. All of the links are listed at the end of the document, so you can maintain full separation between content and its source or reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The links below have been rendered using Reference Style markdown shown in the code box below it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Here is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;, the free encyclopedia and who knew that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chemistry.com&quot; title=&quot;Meet other singles&quot;&gt;Chemistry&lt;/a&gt; dot com would be a dating site!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;table class=&quot;rouge-table&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-gutter gl&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;lineno&quot;&gt;1
2
3
4
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;rouge-code&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;Here is [Wikipedia][1], the free encyclopedia and who knew that [Chemistry][2] dot com would be a dating site!

[1]: &amp;lt;https://en.wikipedia.org/&amp;gt; &quot;Wikipedia&quot;
[2]: &amp;lt;https://www.chemistry.com&amp;gt; &quot;Meet other singles&quot;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;escape-into-html&quot;&gt;Escape into HTML&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw a nifty trick earlier to add color to your markdown text using &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;font&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; but the fact is that you can use full html within Markdown. Below is an embed code that has been iframed into markdown. This is no different from what you would otherwise write into an html document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is an embedded video into markdown!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe style=&quot;width:50%; height:300px&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/P3RXtoYCW4M?rel=0&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2023 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/mark-up-your-text-with-markdown/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/mark-up-your-text-with-markdown/</guid>
        
        
        <category>tech</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chemistry one liners to fall in love with</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Here’s a collection of my all-time favorite one liner jokes in chemistry. Reading through them makes me see the lighter side of chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-one-liners&quot;&gt;The one-liners&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re not part of the solution … &lt;b&gt;you’re part of the precipitate.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Old chemists never die. &lt;b&gt;They just stop reacting!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wait, are all these jokes too basic for you? &lt;b&gt;Because I see no reaction.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are you made of copper and tellurim? &lt;b&gt;Because you’re CuTe.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’d give you some more chemistry jokes, &lt;b&gt;but all the good ones argon.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guys, stop it with the puns. &lt;b&gt;We’ve all sulfured enough.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-bar-collection&quot;&gt;The bar collection&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A neutron walks into a bar and asks the bartender how much a drink costs.
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The bartender says, “For you, no charge.”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helium walks into a bar. The bartender says, “We don’t serve noble gasses here.”
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Helium doesn’t react.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Oxygen, hydrogen, sulfur, sodium, and phosphorous walk into a bar.
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“OH SNaP” says the bartender.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fluorine and chlorine walk into a bar.
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The bartender greets them: “Halo gens”&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-qa-collection&quot;&gt;The Q&amp;amp;A collection&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Click on the fuzzed out text below to reveal the answer to the one liners :)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Know any good chemistry jokes? &lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Na&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Want to hear a joke about nitrogen oxide? &lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;NO!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Want to hear a Potassium joke? &lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;K!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can you tell me the chemical formula for sodium hypobromite? &lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;NaBrO&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the elements of life? &lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Lithium and Iron = LiFe&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do the other elements say about hydrogen? &lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;He’s such a loner!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What kind of fish is made up of only two sodium atoms? &lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;2 Na&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why are chemists great for solving problems? &lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Because they always have a solution!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Did you hear oxygen went on a date with potassium? &lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;It went OK!&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do you call a plant growing in a lab? &lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;A Chemis(tree)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is uranium + fluorine + oxygen? &lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;UFO&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do you laugh at a Helium Joke? &lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;He He He&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How often should you tell a chemistry joke? &lt;span class=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Periodically.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;finally-a-classic-video-that-never-gets-old&quot;&gt;Finally, a classic video that never gets old&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6aK2CKrdjbE?start=6&amp;amp;showinfo=0&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; Do not do this in your chemistry lab though&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2023 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>/chemistry-jokes/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/chemistry-jokes/</guid>
        
        <category>fun stuff</category>
        
        
        <category>chemistry</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
